[Music]
so this is a film that's part of our
sense making series on rebel wisdom and
i'm joined by jesse single and katie
herzog
of the blocked and reported podcast
welcome guys
um cool so we're going to be talking
about the kind of ongoing death
of journalism the collapse of
institutional authority
and big questions like that you've
started up your podcast blocked and
reported at
probably about the right time i'd say a
very
opportune moment could you i'd love if
you could just introduce yourselves very
briefly and talk a little bit about what
the podcast is for before we go into the
details of
the collapse of the media
yeah jesse you want to start sure yeah
i'm um
excuse me jesse single i'm a
contributing writer at new york magazine
former staffer there i've written a lot
about behavioral science i'm
finishing up a book about behavioral
science called the quick fix that will
be out
next year and yeah katie and i started
this podcast just because we had
mostly because we had observed certain
trends going on online
that concerned us with regard to you
know people's inability to have
substantive conversations and and just
discuss the world the way most people do
over dinner table most even just the way
most left of center people do over the
dinner table
and before i can get to katie i just
want to be clear to your viewers my
jufro is not normally so poofy
this is like a quarantine type situation
uh you're actually lucky that you're
getting jessie with a shirt normally he
likes to record topless
um my name is katie herzog and i was
until
until pandemic i was a staff writer at
the stranger which is seattle's
alt weekly or alt bi-weekly i suppose
now um and before that i
worked for i was a staff writer at grist
which is a digital magazine that covers
climate change and the environment um
yeah like jesse i'm
also sort of interested in in the moment
that we're in right now we're both
interested in human behavior and
psychology and so while the rest of the
world
is uh is collapsing it feels like um
jesse and i took the opportunity to
capitalize on it and it's working out
pretty well for us with this podcast
awesome and i mean we're all three of us
journalists so this might get a little
bit inside baseball
so we're going to try and kind of keep
it as big picture as possible but i
think there is
a lot of framing that we need to do kind
of just going over the the recent
history which
feels like there's there's a huge amount
even in the last two weeks
and i'd really direct people to your
podcast if they want to kind of double
click on any of it
but in particular the the new york times
um the the op-ed editor there
left after some big um kind of rebellion
inside the paper
seems to have been led by mostly the
kind of the news staff there was a tweet
storm by barry weiss
who's an opinion writer there
controversial opinion writer there
or controversial to people inside the
paper she originally
coined she wrote the original article
about the intellectual dark web that
people might be familiar with
um and i think she she laid out in a
series of tweets kind of what she
thought was going on inside the
newsrooms
largely a kind of generational divide
between sort of the new
more woke journalists and an older kind
of liberal class of journalists
and then there's a matt tybee piece
which talked about i think eight
different revolts inside newsrooms that
seem to follow a similar pattern over
the last couple of weeks
there was a tweet by mati iglesias who
was one of the original founders of vox
where he basically said he'd have to
apologize for saying that this was a
problem just
confined to university campuses so all
of this stuff was coming kind of thick
and fast
um how would you you summarize it and we
can kind of double click on any of those
and go into the details of it but how
would you summarize
what's been going on over the last
couple of weeks go for a case uh i would
call what's going on
a part of an element of what i see as an
ongoing moral panic
um that has taken over lots of
institutions across the world
particularly the western world
um that seems to really have sunk its
claws into journalism
and what we've been observing over the
past couple weeks a lot of us have been
observing for years and
it has just sort of broken open in a way
that i think is more visible to the
public right now which is
frankly a bit of a relief that this
thing that
that that jesse and i have been writing
about and sort of trying to warn people
about for years is now um is now open
um so it's been wild to watch and uh it
feels very destabilizing but also at
least people are talking about it now
and acknowledging some people at least
are acknowledging that this this trend
is uh israel yeah i think katie's giving
me slightly too much credit because i
i think i in areas where i had done
reporting i had noticed a certain
tendency to not treat questions
journalistically
and to to really tip things too far in
the activist direction
i don't think i realized how bad it was
until around the time we started the
podcast maybe even after
um there's a sense that
certain important norms of liberal
values and particularly journalistic
values are being tossed aside because
it's a bit of a revolutionary moment and
my argument was it is that if if you
care about the world and you want to
improve it and you
care about things like police brutality
and racial justice
it has to be grounded in in liberal
values and in journalism and in
science and a lot of what's going on now
is not that in part because people are
afraid that if they say the wrong thing
and this happened this week or last week
a kid
at a data scientist tweeted a respected
study showing that
in certain contexts um violent protests
could be shown to not work
relative to violent protest which you
know it's complicated subject
he got fired because people said they
were offended that he would even suggest
that
and and the academic study was by a
black academic as well i think
omar was so yeah i think he's biracially
identifies as black
yeah i mean that that was one of the
most kind of
that seemed to be one of the most kind
of intense examples i was going to come
to this a bit later in the conversation
but i think i'm going to come to it now
because katie you mentioned that
it feels like everyone now realizes that
there's a problem
it's not that's not strictly true i mean
there was an article by nathan robinson
and current affairs that basically sort
of
pooh-poohed the whole idea that there is
this moral panic and was just saying
that it's being used to attack the left
and if you look into these questions
it's it's overblown or it's just
right-wing agitators
so there is there are still people kind
of saying no this is this isn't even
happening
yeah that's definitely true and there
has been that's been ongoing so
anybody who's written about
quote-unquote cancel culture over the
past year so every time there's an
article or a piece about it there's a
backlash to that and there's
people particularly people on the left
who say no cancer culture isn't real
cancer culture is just
uh it's just you know a response to
criticism
um you know it's uh it's right grifter
is trying to
trying to sort of shield themselves from
any sort of criticism so that has been
ongoing
i have seen people who before have said
like cancer culture isn't real in the
past couple weeks say okay it's real but
it doesn't really matter
um so yes there is there the denial
continues but i think it's it's harder
it's harder to deny for most people both
inside and outside of the
echo chambers that we live in i
personally have had a few people
actually
do sort of the remarkable thing of
apologize to me in the past couple weeks
were saying you know i thought you were
crazy when you were writing about sort
of the excesses of cancer culture
over the past couple years and now that
i see that you're right so um that's a
new experience for me
but yeah i think you're right people are
definitely there's still a contingent of
people who are very invested in denying
that this uh
this trend is is happening
yeah what did you make of that article
jesse
you know there's been sort of a long
this is a whole sub genre of articles
now that tries to make this out as
though on the one hand
are you know reactionary white men and
maybe katie is an honorary
reactionary white man i identify as a
reactionary
white man there we go um so so it's just
this totally oversimplified view where
on the one hand are those
evil reactionary white people who just
want to continue being racist without
consequences
on the other hand are the people
fighting for social justice who just
want them to stop being racist
this is a complete oversimplification
because when we talk about cancer
culture however you define it i
you know i people like dave chappelle
are not affected by cancer culture
because they're rich and powerful even
people like me much lower on the sort of
power ladder
if anything controversies help my career
i'm much more worried about you know
david shore the kid who got he's 28
years old he got fired by his employer
because of a dumb twitter blow up
the washington post just wrote an
article about a year and a half incident
where a
woman wore a ridiculous costume
to a halloween party with blackface she
got sort of uh
ostracized from the party she left she
was humiliated that wasn't enough they
had to dig it up a year and a half later
now she's fired she's a
40 or 50 something year old woman who
will probably not have a job until her
social security days because
it wasn't enough that she was humiliated
so when we talk about cancer culture
it's very punitive
impulse and if you have money in power
you will generally be protected from it
so it's
it's more vulnerable people who are more
likely to be um
affected by it so that's that's usually
my response when people claim this isn't
a thing or that we shouldn't worry about
it
right when this is always the response
when people the
people the people who say that cancer
culture doesn't exist they'll bring up
you know like jesse said examples like
dave chappelle what they don't bring up
is all the people that we haven't heard
of or these sort of
minor non-famous characters who have
been pushed out of
their careers or of the employment
system altogether
and i guess it's just a convenient sort
of like you just point to the one who's
doing well and like jesse i think
controversy has been good for my career
but for people who
don't have sort of ambitions to be in
the public eye it can be
terrible for your career and for your
you know your social life your friends
drop you your family
shunts you it's it's a phenomenon that's
happening but it's uh
some people certainly still deny it yeah
and i want to kind of
focus on the the moment right now i mean
you guys and rebel wisdom like i've done
interviews with brett
weinstein uh going back a couple of
years i'm very well aware of these
arguments i think a lot of people
watching will be familiar with the
backstory and
how how much this has been growing over
the last few years
but just right now i i had a a couple of
texts from friends in newsrooms
saying that things have shifted just in
the last couple of weeks
that the kind of language that's being
used and when
in the uk we didn't really have that the
the same kind of language as you have in
the states like the allyship and
people of color and that's not really
english
that hasn't been english terminology and
he's saying that the
the the tone of just the the nature of
the language in the newsroom has changed
dramatically even in the last two weeks
and the atmosphere in editorial meetings
he described
as incendiary and that
what are you hearing from people from
from friends or former colleagues in
in newsrooms i mean it's the same
yeah yeah i heard uh yesterday from a a
friend in a newsroom that at his
newsroom they have started
they started a book club but the book
club
it was sort of posed as like there's
going to be a book club in this in this
newsroom but it has devolved into or
maybe evil
into a book club about just like racial
justice issues
so he was telling me about a meeting of
this book club where white people were
sitting around and just talking about
their like it was like an aaa meeting
they were saying like like one by one
going by like my name is katie and i'm a
racist
um which is a very bizarre thing to
imagine happening in any workplace
much less a newsroom um but it is
happening
yeah and i think um i've also heard from
people who just don't really think they
can do their jobs well anymore because
like if you're covering
one example is just like the protests in
the states which have been
i think overwhelmingly peaceful and i
think they've trended toward becoming
more peaceful but
uh if you're a journalist or you're sort
of a public policy analyst
you might have something to say about
the the corner of them that weren't
peaceful and you might be able to want
to
you will likely want to be able to speak
openly about the effects of that
violence or how that violence has
affected businesses that gotten burned
down
just really basic forms of journalism
and activism and
policy analysis that people now feel
afraid to do
so it's just a sort of some kind of
spiral of silence thing going on maybe
and these aren't
people who are seeking to express like
far-right views or anything they're
seeking to express views that a month
ago felt unremarkable
yeah i think that spiral of silence
piece is really interesting
because i remember some of the coverage
of the new york times situation
included people saying well on our on
our slack channels no one's supporting
uh or no one no one's speaking out
against the
i think was the sacking of was it tom
cotton or uh no cotton was the senator
james
so james bennett was sacked but what's
amazing about that is these slack
channels where they're saying
no one's speaking up in the other
direction are in real time getting
leaked by liberal twitter users
and inevitably there's always an article
later on this time by vice
in another case by huffington post
leaking the entire contents of these so
of course you're not going to speak up
because then you'll be the one
dissenting voice in the the inevitable
huffpo or buzzfeed art it's just very
bad faith to say that because people
aren't speaking up internally
i've i've talked to multiple time
staffers who are concerned about what's
going on and they would not speak up
because what's the incentive
and do you have a sense of why
journalism has
do you think that it was sort of
structural issues in journalism that
have that have kind of got it to the
point where it's been
taken over by this kind of situation how
how do you frame it
it sort of feels a bit like a kind of
mirror of the of the whole pandemic to
me like a week a week host being taken
over via virus
in double quick time
just do you want to check that yeah i
mean yeah we've talked about this a
little too but some people
there's just like two simple catchphrase
that particularly people on the right
use like
go won't go broke as though people are
are these journalis these outlets are
struggling because of their
political stances but i think katie and
i both think the opposite is true is
that the structural problems with
journalism go so far beyond
ideology there's just an entire business
model has collapsed a business model
that
30 years ago was such that you know the
baltimore sun and the boston globe could
have farm bureaus which is unthinkable
now
i think as an institution collapses the
culture inside is going to get very
weird and and in this case what you see
basically is that whatever concerns
upper middle class graduates of elite
universities is more and more
what they care about uh and that is
where wokeness resides
so yeah i think i think obviously they
feed back into one another because like
maybe people will stop reading certain
publications as they get less and less
trustworthy but overall i'm much more in
the camp of um
go broke awoke than vice versa
yeah the structural stuff is a much
bigger deal and it's all and this goes
back
decades this goes back to craigslist and
then social media i mean the business
models have
totally collapsed i mean just for
instance like the seattle times the big
sort of daily paper
here 20 years ago had 5 000 staffers
today they have sold their buildings
they exist on two floors in a tiny
building it was
apparently uh the the publisher was
offered like 730 million dollars in the
early early 2000s
from you know gannett or some like major
corporation to buy this paper and today
it is almost
worthless um so that i mean that's
really the issue is that the industry is
failing and the response
the response of that has been for
everybody to sort of go kind of crazy in
some ways um
but it is not i think yeah the the
structural issues really precede
sort of the um the other things that are
happening within methodist and i also
think this is also
part of a broader a broader trend in the
culture a lot of which has to do with
sort of backlash against donald trump
and a lot of fear about
um you know him sort of ushering into uh
people think that he's going to usher in
you know a new danger of fascism or
authoritarianism
into into the into the nation and so
there's been this sort of
ben smith from the new york times calls
it resistance journalism and i do think
there has been a trend over the past
couple years for journalists to really
sort of see
themselves more or maybe they still see
themselves as journalists but they've
really turned into activists
um and you know and everybody sort of
wants to be on the right side of history
we're in such a weird moment in time
that people are deeply concerned about
the country
understandably and they want to sort of
do the right thing
but do the right thing in this case
often means sort of shaking off these
the values of journalism that have
existed for a long time
i want to talk a little bit more about
that dynamic because it seems
i'm thinking about the intercept case as
well where one
member of staff basically criticized
another and the and the other member of
staff ended up having to apologize that
the lee fang
was was the member of staff had to
apologize but if you think about the
imbalance of power now with social media
any member of staff could criticize
you publicly even if you're a senior
journalist
and and you you're now potentially so
anything that can happen any any single
uh
editorial process that happens someone
could leak at any point
so what what does that do to journalism
what does that what's
what does that cultural fear look and
feel like
start a podcast luckily i would hate to
be in journalism right now
yeah totally i mean free from from these
environments now because we started this
podcast
that that nobody has leaked or leaked
our chats yet although if jesse pisses
me off too much maybe i'll do it
they're incredibly celebrating like you
said it's a culture of fear
right um this this culture of fear and
it does
influence not just you know how people
relate to each other within the
workplace but also what gets covered
and i think that's a problem as well you
know i guess he mentioned this
washington post piece yesterday about a
woman a total like a non-famous
non-public figure
who wore an offensive halloween costume
two years ago
i would imagine there was probably some
some people who
within the post who you know objected to
the publication
of this and like ruining this woman's
life for over what is
uh like really a microaggression but
what incentive would anybody have to
speak out about that
when the culture is going like full
steam in this one direction
and anybody who pushes back on that is
accused of being
racist or a bigot or against the you
know on the wrong side of history
there's just
absolutely no incentive to sort of speak
your truth um to use a
phrase uh borrowed from from progress
progressive um because the the cost is
just too high
yeah do you have anything to add to that
jesse
no just just i i i found some of the
reporting on this remarkable
particularly a vox story where
the author didn't try to reach out to
barry weiss and didn't try to reach out
to anyone affected which
if if i am not particularly well
connected in journalism if
i am aware of time staffers pissed off
by what's going on there has to be a lot
more of them so i just
it's the quality of the of of
progressive journalism reporting on
itself at the moment that also drives me
crazy because i it's like
it just seems there's sort of no uh
adults in the room
yeah i think that was a vox article that
sort of framed itself as
the explainer of all you need to know
about what's going on
and i think i i remember you sort of
saying that it was a it was a really
one-sided take yeah on
on what was happening do you have a
sense of what matt iglesias was
referring to when he said
that he he needed to apologize for
thinking it was just confined to
university campuses he seemed to be
referring to something happening inside
box
yeah um i think that's accurate i think
there's stuff going on in box
that sort of wouldn't want to see more
than that
there was another guy at fox um zac
champ
who what jesse do you remember what the
tweet was exactly no it was jeremiah
lopez uh
spelled german lopez who said something
similar to ignacius that um
basically i forget what he was
responding with strongly implying that
he agrees that there's something
going on there um but i think you could
basically take what happened at the
times in a very public spectacular way
and
imagine a thousand versions of that
going on more quietly at
any modern media outlet with a lot of
sort of younger staffers
and that would be accurate enough right
and
and so vox bought new york magazine and
new york magazine
is where andrew sullivan writes and
andrew sullivan has
uh apparently there's basically like a
committee of like young staffers who now
vet his columns and have the power to
veto
what andrew sullivan writes and i don't
think that's because vox took it over
i i'd heard rumors about this since uh
well before box took a
uh new york magazine um but it's a
bizarre bizarre twist
yeah and is it worth sort of unpacking
what happened at the new york times
just for people who maybe aren't
familiar with it
yeah i mean so basically tom cotton
wrote an op-ed saying that the troops
should be called in to quell
uh looters and rioters p it was people
subsequently claimed he was saying
the troops should be called in to just
murder protesters that wasn't what he
said he'd also done some tweets that
were like pretty far right and suggested
maybe he was toning down his true
beliefs in the column the point is
the columns staked out a i would say
right wing position but one that there's
a fair amount of u.s polio and support
for
it gets a little bit fuzzy with question
wording also he's suggesting like
the army gets sent in even in cities
where the governor mayor doesn't want
them which is
you know pretty extreme policy
a bunch of time staffers tweeted in
unison that this column
put black times journalists in danger
which is a very hard thing to
to figure out what that means how tom
cotton publishing this column in the
times versus
breitbart or medium how that's the
difference between journalists being
safe and being in danger and i think
my reaction to this i think katie's was
was partly about
the times bending over backward to
pretend this had been some horrible
editorial breach rather than just a
right-wing call when people freaked out
at
but also it's creepy watching a bunch of
of journalists
you know responsible for bringing us the
truth all tweeting the same thing in
unison that is
questionable at best so it was just i
don't think the times acquitted itself
well during that sorry katie
i think the it's also for people
especially in the uk who might not know
this um tom cotton is a
is a sitting u.s senator um so he is a
a man who actually does power have power
in the world
he does not have the power to
unilaterally send troops into you know
the the streets of the united states
um but he is you know he is a a notable
figure
in this country um and as jesse
mentioned so
all of these time staffers replied in
unison
this piece uh in dangerous black times
journalists or black time staffers or
something like that
and in subsequent recording that was
published actually in the new york times
um the staffers said like the reason we
went with the sort of we went with the
harm angle
for a reason because the you know you
can't just say
i don't like this right because then it
becomes a free speech issue
an intellectual freedom issue so they
found this sort of one like little
narrow narrow position that would allow
them to take a sort of mor
the moral high ground here while while
trying not to appear
as sensors which is exactly what they
were doing
yeah and i think it's worth also
emphasizing there were two pieces that
came out afterwards that i thought were
very
interesting one as you mentioned jesse
that the the polling suggests that
actually what tom cotton was calling for
is actually quite popular
um in in the american public so if
you're basically saying that's not
acceptable you're saying
i've seen up to like 47 of people saying
that that was
that they might have been in favor of
that yeah to be clear that was a
slightly different question but i think
what you're saying is accurate there's
at the very least
would be you would think 40 or 45
support for what he's saying depending
on how you phrase the question was not
for better or worse it was not an
outlier opinion the way some people made
it out to be
yeah and also the the point was made
that that's why you publish things like
that because
actually in retrospect it turned out to
have been premature it turned out to
have been bad advice
and if you stop those opinions being put
out there you don't have a record of
that
actually it's probably not um
it looks certainly premature and maybe
ill-advised in retrospect what he was
arguing for
yeah i mean that is a good point he
happened to be very wrong and and the
the key takeaway here is going to be the
times having made a fool of itself
and sort of acted on acting on
journalistically rather than what the
story should be which is tom cotton was
a reactionary idiot here
yeah and you you deprived the chance of
of actually
that being exposed in the marketplace of
of ideas by
uh preventing him from making the
argument in the first place
i'm interested right and what
well one more point about that so he
like he could have published this on any
right-wing site but he didn't and i
think that's actually a good thing
because
we live in these very narrow media
bubbles and echo chambers so if he had
published this on breitbart or the
federalist or the washington
examiner or whatever it wouldn't have
made a storm people wouldn't have
even like people on the on the left this
would have
made they would it wouldn't be it
wouldn't have registered um
and now people know and the fact that
like the times is like
sort of forcing it's mostly liberal
readership to contend with
these ideas i think is a good thing um
but time staffers obviously disagree
yeah yeah and i wanted to pick up you
mentioned
that they chose a particular angle for
it katie like the sort of
and i think barry wise framed it as
safetyism so going back to jonathan
heights work with the coddling of the
american mind
and the idea that there is a culture of
safetyism i know that you i heard your
in your podcast jesse you kind of
disagreed with barry a little bit on
this
but but you seem to be saying that you
thought it was safetyism katie is that
right
i think i think safety is excuse me i
think safetyism is an
angle i think they were trying to turn
it into a labor issue um
just to to appear as though as though it
was
not about censorship i think it was sort
of a convenient angle that they took i
do think that
safetyism is very widespread um
especially in sort of
elite institutions people it's sort of
uh the quintessential safety
environment as a college and all of
these people sort of that come from
academia
or at least are college-educated but i
think it was an excuse
um you know and and one that that seemed
legitimate to an awful lot of people
why did you disagree with that as a as
an explanation jesse
i don't think we disagree that much i
think saying that the column could
harm black journalists isn't is an
instant
i can't talk is a manifestation of
safetyism i thought in terms of framing
what the opposing
sides are i don't think it's true that
one side is like safetyism the other is
not like for example i think a lot of
conservatives have have really bad
issues of safetyism with their own when
they say
you know flag burning does some real
harm to america or colin kaepernick
taking a knee
i they have all sorts of stuff they
freak out at so i just i think it's a
natural human inclination and i think
as we laid out on the podcast you can
get a little bit more specific in
journalistic context of the norms that
are are being fought over here and and
that includes norms like
you know uh how far to the right an
opinion are we willing to publish or or
should we judge stuff from the
ideological outgroup at
a higher more stringent standard for
quality stuff like that
i'd love to um go a little bit back over
your
your personal history because you've
both had kind of
relatively high profile run-ins with
you've both written about
trans and then had quite high profile
run-ins or at least caused controversy
with
with trans activists i'd love if you
could just summarize that
that backstory and we can kind of ask a
little bit about that
yeah sure um so in 2017
i was a freelancer um and i wrote a
piece for the stranger called the d
transitioners and it was what it sounds
like it was a piece about people who
transitioned from
one sex or gender to the other and then
and then change their mind
and and transition back um and this was
a
it was deeply reported it wasn't an
opinion piece i
i took every sort of um precaution in
terms of
getting happily trans voices in there
it's talking about how
transition you know does seem to
alleviate gender dysphoria for an awful
lot of people
um i had trans sensitivity readers but
there was still this sort of massive
firestorm and i don't know how many
people who hated the piece actually
read the piece um and that's this is
actually how i met jesse for the first
time i
er through email like i when i was
working on the piece i got in touch with
jesse to
to try to interview him um for a second
that ultimately didn't didn't get
published
um and there was just this like people
were actually burning stacks of the
paper
there were flyers up in coffee shops in
my neighborhood calling me transphobic
and that really changed the course of my
career
for the better to be honest i mean
there's some irony here is that the
the freak out that everybody had about
it
really elevated my profile it got me a
lot more opportunities i ultimately was
offered a staff shop at the paper
and i don't think any of that would have
happened if people had just sort of read
the piece and said like i disagree with
it but no big deal you know um
and that that happens it happens sort of
sort of frequently
um you know it's emotionally difficult
to go through this experience but
ultimately it was it was
you know probably the best the best move
in my career um
but it's still i have gotten since that
piece was published and i would say
there's nothing transphobic about
it that is my reputation if you ask like
a random person who
reads the stranger on the streets of
seattle who katie
herzog is they would probably say she's
the transphobe which is
patently false um but that's just sort
of what happens you know
anybody who who has the temerity
questions some aspects of
of the the current trans dogma is
automatically pegged as a bigot
um and you know this happens
not just with not just with journalists
it's happened with academics with jk
rowling
recently of course um just a lot of
people have gone through sort of a
similar experience
uh so my yeah mine was also about trans
issues it was really a pair of articles
in one of them i looked into the
allegations against the doctor who ran a
gender clinic in toronto
he had been accused of conversion
therapy and his clinic had been shut
down and he had been fired
a lot of kids had lost access to their
care uh
the accusations against him were almost
entirely false
one of them was completely wrong it was
a misunderstanding on the part of the
accuser who
acknowledged that after i pointed out
inconsistencies
in his story um i was seen as defending
the indefensible it was
other journalists seem to think that
because this guy had been accused of
transphobia and we all know transphobia
is wrong i should just take the activist
views at face value instead i looked
into them and i found they were false
and i did what journalists do or
used to do and printed a story that went
against the common wisdom that i'm very
proud of to this day
then a couple summers ago today's
actually the two day anniversary of it
facebook informed me
uh happy anniversary jesse thank you i
had a cover story in the atlantic about
uh gender dysphoria among young people
and
what the process should be look like for
a 12 or 13 year old in particular
and especially one with sort of complex
other mental health problems
you know what should the process look
like before we put them on hormones
before we consider surgery for older
teenagers
it's a 12 or 13 000 word story that i'm
immensely proud of and i was the
beneficiary of like
expert fact checking and there's nothing
transphobic about it but is viewed as
basically like at least adjacent to a
hate crime for even suggesting
that some people regret transition which
some people do or that some kids are
rushed into transition which they are
so yeah that um it's sort of the same
deal as katie where
our situation socially we're different
because i have like very
vanilla obama liberal friends and
katie's from like a more radical queer
community or once at the time so i
didn't i didn't lose real friends over
it but a subset of
left of center journalists uh still view
me as
just a evil bigot and when i try to ask
them to point to stuff i've actually
written to support that assessment
they can't so it's just sort of a meme
at this point and one of the things
that's been very frustrating and
enlightening
is watching professional journalists
sort of launch accusations without any
evidence and without caring about the
evidence so
i think katie and i are extremely sad
journalism is burning down for
structural reasons but like
you know it's gratifying to be able to
build their own platform and not have to
worry about those sorts of people at all
yeah jessie's jesse's firestorm is much
much bigger than i mean
lena dunham calls you an asshole right i
mean you are an asshole but
she doesn't actually know you she called
me that i think in the third person
sense not to me but uh
yeah it got pretty intense i think yours
was worse in terms of sort of the
interpersonal damage
mine might have temporarily been higher
profile but i'm not sure
right yeah because i mean you you both
sort of
um i think are saying that it was on the
on the whole sort of a net positive for
your careers but
i'm interested in how it was to go
through that experience because i know
there aren't that many people who have a
um what did jezebel
jezebel wrote a story called what is
what is jesse singles fucking deal
yeah yeah exactly well and that's
investigative journalism
so in that story the did they find out
though if they found out that
they did it that's my biggest secret if
it gets out what my fucking deal is my
career is over um
i'm gonna end up writing that piece well
that was a good example because
katie do you remember the author's name
off the herron walker herron walker
yeah she she spams my email with
um emails that just say what's your
fucking deal what's your deal what's
your deal what's your deal no attempt to
do an actual interview
i'm obviously not gonna respond to that
then they run a piece that gets my views
wrong
that that absolutely misrepresents what
i said there were similar pieces in
slate
and and the new york times so it
obviously sucks
to have a bunch of people on twitter
call you a bigot and and
you know i don't know if it was
harassment but it was annoying at the
very least i didn't get death threats or
anything uh or i only got one death
threat from it well borderline from a
journalist actually
but seeing your work misrepresented in
mainstream outlets
that just don't care what you actually
wrote because it's so important
for them to chime in on the right side
of the controversy i found it insane
that i had to deal with writing a letter
to the editor to correct something in
the new york times like
you know this isn't what we call a first
world problem like i
very good life i'm lucky but it's just
it it
it saps away your soul a little bit to
watch people just lie about you without
any sort of consequences
and it also for me it was also sort of
destabilizing in the sense that i had
previously lived in a world where i
trusted the media
you know where i trusted um people to
interpret things to like read things
before they interpret them and that i
was i was just sort of
shown um in a very visceral way that you
basically can't trust you can't trust
what you read oftentimes and that has
that has been
reinforced over the over the last few
years and as jesse
jesse mentioned i think it had a higher
social cost for me because
i'm gay and most of the social networks
that i existed in
for my entire adulthood have been sort
of radical queer circles
um and i was basically shunned by my
social networks
and i still am i had i had there was on
on one occasion i was walking up the
street um
near my house and i saw saw an ex of
mine who i had been on like very good
terms with someone i had remained close
with after we broke up
we were walking on the same side of the
street and she just i was passing her
she just turned around
you know it was like i wasn't there um
in seattle is sort of a
like notoriously pacific city so i
wasn't
super worried about people um at first i
was sort of worried about being like
accosted in the street um
but what i realized is that people were
more likely to like dive into the bushes
when they saw me coming and then shit
talk me online
that's more of a more of a seattle uh
go-to response to any sort of conflict
but it was very um it was very isolating
uh
i felt totally friendless because i was
all of a sudden totally friendless
and it hasn't really rebounded i i think
that i still am sort of a
um i think a lot of my sort of former
friends and and allies would consider me
sort of a pariah or a thought criminal
or they probably think i'm like an
all-right neo-nazi there there are still
i mean
there are stickers up in seattle there
are like four different versions of
stickers in seattle calling me some
version of a bigot
um just recently during the uh all of
this sort of protest
so my office in seattle my former office
is in
chaz the capitol hill autonomous zone
that has sort of made international news
it's this area in seattle that has been
taken over by protesters and um
and uh so my office is right is right in
that and on the
one of the first days of the sort of
protest down there the um
i don't know maybe it was riots down
there maybe it was protest i don't know
how much looting was happening
um someone graffitied fuck herzog on the
door of my former office
and this is all a response to
you know this one piece and subsequently
like once i got hired at the paper i
continued to write things that
um i didn't think were particularly
inflammatory but a lot of people did
just things like you know questioning
sort of the excesses of me too
writing about concern for due process
concern for you know the
um diminishing values of free speech
these liberal values that i think are
incredibly important um and so my
reputation
within seattle is i think basically as a
as a
you know like a literal nazi um which is
very
a very strange sort of rebranding it's
not what i ever would have expected you
know like
even five or five or six years ago um so
it's been weird and how would you
describe your political views
maybe to both of you i i'm just sort of
a
like a milktoast liberal i mean probably
farther to the left than
most americans um my values have changed
a little bit i think i am since all this
sort of happened one of the
sort of more interesting but also
destabilizing and disorienting
parts of this experience was that
before i wrote this piece and before the
response to this piece i had sort of the
blanket assumption that everything
on the left was correct and everything
on the right was wrong
and the response to my piece sort of
opened my eyes to the fact that my side
my ideological allies my tribe
could be wrong because i knew they were
wrong about this piece
um and and once you see that there's
sort of no going back
and that doesn't mean that i've become a
republican i haven't for sure
i think i have drifted towards more sort
of civil libertarian values not so much
in a financial
sense but um as the culture has changed
over the past couple years i have become
much more concerned about civil
liberties as the left has
in many cases sort of you know even the
aclu has sort of
given up on the values of free speech
and free expression um
and so i think my politics have changed
a little bit but in terms of how i vote
i'm just sort of a
basic like milk dose democrat um you
know
in 2016 i supported bernie sanders i
voted for hillary clinton this time
around i will vote for whoever
you know it will be joe biden presumably
but i will vote for whoever is running
against donald trump
so pretty just sort of standard
normative politics
um that were you know if i looked at
polling i'm probably further
you know further to the left than than
the vast majority of americans but i'm
not like uh
you know i'm not a rose emoji marxist or
anything like that
yeah i mean i think i'm somewhat similar
i guess like if it was we're talking
about the
other redistributive questions we
basically no one ever talks about
because we don't
it's always who dressed in blackface at
the halloween party in terms of who
whose tax money goes where
or at least i'm oversimplifying but not
by much these days um
i think i'm pretty far to the left i
mean i uh i was torn between bernie
sanders and liz warren
again if you actually laid us out on
sort of some spectrum of american
opinion we would
both be pretty far to the left and i'm
you know i don't know really what to
call myself other than a liberal or
leftist or progressive i
i i wish that on cultural stuff like
cancel culture stuff
what katie's describing sort of cultural
libertarianism i think should be a part
of progressivism or a part of the left
in part because
if we're on the left we should care
about people who have less power
and any punitive system of dealing with
crime with infractions at work with
microaggressions
is going to come down harder on more
vulnerable people like again
dave chappelle is not the victim of
cancer culture he could do 15 deeply
offensive segments and still have
millions of dollars so
it i resent the fact you know no hate
for libertarians but i'm not a
libertarian and i don't think i should
have to adopt the
cultural libertarian label just to make
arguments like
some hapless woman shouldn't lose her
job over a bad halloween costume a year
and a half ago and i think the left
harms itself greatly by leaving that
territory for the
right to claim sometimes in a bad faith
way because the right has its own
canceled culture but
why would we see just like these aspects
of basic human dignity and and the
chance for redemption all the stuff that
like
gives humanity potential i think that
frustrates me
yeah i would i'd like to add one thing i
think in an ideal world these labels
we would get rid of the labels all
together and i know that's never going
to happen
but i've sort of drifted away from
sort of wrapping my identity up with my
political affiliations or my political
positions so
for for one thing i i no longer would
call myself a feminist or an
environmentalist or
these labels that that had some more
meaning to me a few years ago
because i've found that when your
identity is wrapped up in a movement or
a label like this it becomes harder to
evaluate
the position based on their merits and
not sort of your own sort of emotional
response
um you know to the label itself you know
liberals good conservatives bad or
vice versa or whatever it is so i think
in an ideal world
you know we would look at every issue
for its merits and not uh based on who's
making the argument but we don't live in
that world
um so i'm gonna consider i'm gonna keep
calling myself a liberal because that's
how i vote and those are sort of the
policies i typically agree with um but i
wish that i wish that we didn't have to
i wish that
that sort of we could do away with these
designations and um and just look at
issues without this sort of added
baggage of these labels
yeah i think i'd agree i mean i i was
brought up in a very left-wing family
i've always kind of considered myself
um we don't quite use liberal in the
same way as you
use it there as a political affiliation
but i'm certainly a disaffected
uh left winger but i'm also and i think
i heard you refer to this jesse in one
of the recent podcasts
wary of how that kind of can be
weaponized as well
like the dave rubin i've been quite
critical in the past of dave rubin
for that just the sort of singular focus
on the left
yeah and the faults of the left like
even that kind of disaffected liberal
kind of
identity can be sort of part of the
weaponized as part of a culture war
which i'm very wary of
yeah i mean you see people katie and i
have talked about this like people who
are like well
political correctness has gone so far
i'm just going to vote for trump i can't
stand this anymore which to me is a
severe misunderstanding of power or an
inability to put things in perspective
because like
on the whole if i have to live with a
world with
more cancer culture but biden rather
than trump is choosing supreme court
nominees and who to stock the
environmental protection agency with
you know i would choose that world it's
just i think if you're in journalism or
academia you you need to be vigilant
because stuff is getting really bad and
you need to be able to
fight two battles at once but i think
there is this sort of cottage industry
of like
um people who posit themselves as
disillusioned liberals but if you
actually watch what they say and write
like
the furthest their liberalism goes is
saying they're well ruben's case is gay
or like in favor of gay marriage which
like in 2020 is like
not a particularly lefty position so so
yeah i'm wary of that and i
i do think that i what i hope our
podcast will do is
the the sort of discourse landscape
mainstream circles is so bare and i hope
that we can sort of be like a net to
prevent people from falling through
towards sort of more
reactionary stuff because we again the
worst thing you can say about our
politics is is we sometimes have boring
liberal tendencies but we have
uh i think donald trump's election was a
fucking disaster for i don't know if we
can sway
donald trump's election was a disaster
for america and the most important thing
is to make sure
uh doesn't happen again
yeah and i i guess you're in a really
interesting position now
um how long is it since you set the
podcast up
a month and four days uh well the
podcast a few months the patreon a month
and four days
wow and you've already you're already
doing pretty well i'd urge anyone
listening to
check it out and to to sign up on
patreon um
but it but it does seem like you're in a
very interesting position because
you've created an environment where you
can speak your minds in
in a in a time where a lot of
journalists feel that they can't
how do you sort of see it now where do
you sort of see
yourselves and um how do you see the
future of the
of the podcast
um i think the future for the podcast
is is bright as long as jesse and i
managed not to kill each other um
it's been just uh it's been really
remarkable i i
if you had asked me you know when i was
laid off during a pandemic if this was
ultimate would ultimately be
good for my career i would have thought
you were crazy but it the response has
been really remarkable to see
and i think part of that i you know i
hear from people jesse and i both hear
from people all the time who say
i can't have these conversations with my
friends
i don't know what to do i feel like i'm
going crazy
thank you for making me feel less crazy
and yeah we're i don't think we're doing
anything particularly remarkable but
there's something right now about just
like speaking honestly about our
observations about the world that is
really resonating with people because
they're not getting that anywhere else
um and so for me you know coming from a
staff writer position if i had been
covering
the protests and and the pandemic and
everything that's been happening over
the past couple months within my my
former job
i would have felt really constrained
about what i was able to say and what i
wasn't able to say and i mostly wrote
opinion pieces
um for the paper but my opinion just
wasn't aligned with a lot of my
colleagues
and there's such pressure to conform and
such sort of internal sort of
you know conflict when there's one
person who is
who has a slightly slightly different
you know
perspective on things that it feels very
constraining
and so now i feel free for the first
time
ever you know and and the only person i
have to really worry about is pissing
off is jessie
and uh luckily he's pretty tolerant for
now
for now we'll see how long it lasts yeah
i mean i would just echo everything
she's saying for me
it's a huge relief to just to be able to
vent about this stuff
and also just the emails we're getting
they're like they're thanking us as
though we're providing some life
preserving or sandy preserving
service which is crazy because i know
we're not
i think we put out a good product but
it's just a sign that like mainstream
outlets are not providing this very
basic service of just normal analysis
and journalism so
i think our success like is tied
directly to the fact that jerk like so
many outlets have just gone off the
rails and it's it's crazy that we should
be able to
quickly build out a podcast that you
know will support
almost a full time like it's it's just
crazy and it i just want to
make it clear because i want the
take-home point i want to be here
is not that we have launched a
successful podcast as perhaps i am with
that but that that what the hell are
other outlets doing like how can
between us and the other outlets that
are
the other podcasts that are
significantly left but not really into
like the super woke thing
there's clearly a market of this people
will hand over their money
the cost of a subscription to like a
streaming service just for our podcast
what does that tell you about
what what the market isn't serving right
now i don't i don't think it's because
katie and i are particularly geniuses
although i wish i could say that was the
answer
yeah and just just as a final piece i'd
like to read from an article that was
written today
unheard published something that speaks
to what you were just saying katie and i
think
i'd be interested in your thoughts on
this of sort of the response to
trump's victory in 2016 and also why
this is significant it's not just a kind
of
um inside journalism story this is this
is a lot of
the taste makers and the opinion formers
of an awful lot of people
have a lot of um and a lot of values
so yeah i just want to read this quote
this isn't just a media story it's a
story about the epistemological rupture
in the u.s polity that was provoked by
the events of 2016
and has since grown more extreme in
isolation these moral panics and
collective mental
breakdowns can be difficult to make
sense of but when you see them through
the prism of america's current status as
a rapidly declining hegemonic power
it all becomes much more intelligible
i think that that's sort of
frighteningly
uh astute um things are crazy and you
know and obviously
a lot of the same elements are happening
in the uk um but you know there's a
there's trump or there's boris johnson
or something and then there's an immense
backlash um
to try to sort of to right to right the
ship
um but then there you know there's the
backlash to the backlash and the writing
of the ship might end up you know just
tossing the ship over to the other
direction
yeah there's definitely something some
sort of epistemic breach going on his
that quote reminded me of um
we don't know again again this whole
thing but they saw the covington
catholic scandal from a year or two ago
where a bunch of kids were filmed
at first it seemed like they were
mocking and harassing this native
american elder
they weren't like the progressive media
was completely wrong about it but there
was this real unwillingness on the part
of many progressives to see what was
before us what was before our own eyes
and for me that was like a radicalizing
moment because i just realized
to look at a video and not see what's on
the video to continue to say that this
was
like a borderline hate crime rather than
you know a few kids did that the
tomahawk
chop which is a little offensive but
thousands of people do it every year at
us
sporting events that i think episomic
breach is really right so when you talk
about things like ruptures in the times
newsroom
if you could really dig into them and
figure out the arguments people are
making they have to do with questions
like
do you do you challenge the testimonies
of people from marginalized groups what
constitutes knowledge what constitutes
sufficient evidence
and i think for a long time on the left
we didn't really we ignored that there
were these breaches but um
trump and then i think the pandemic
mixed with the
protest has like been this trump-like
event almost that has just
starting to really crack up the left in
ways that could be
i think dangerous but there's also some
potential upside so i'm just very
curious
and scared about how things are gonna go
it's a good time to be an independent
podcaster who's contrarian left
i'll say that cool thank you very much
for joining me
uh definitely go and check out the
podcast i'll put the details in the show
notes below
and i'm sure we'll catch up again and
see how bad things have got in
a few months time thank you thank you
thank you
thanks for having us rebel wisdom was
set up to make sense of the world
at a deeper level than the mainstream
media it was built for these times of
crisis and change
which is why we want to do what we can
to meet the challenge of the times
more films and also for our rebel wisdom
members
weekly sense making calls with our
amazing interviewees
and also we're introducing the wisdom
gym
a place to practice some of the skills
that we've talked about on the channel
thanks for watching see you soon